Guide to the Neil Wesson Papers ALBA.117
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Neil Wesson Papers
1937-1974
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wesson, Neil, 1906-1974
ALBA.117
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Neil Wesson, nee Nathan Weisenfeld (1906-1974) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and later served as a weapons sergeant and reconnaissance scout in the United States Army during World War II. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence from Wesson to his first wife, Sarah Wesson, written during his service in World War II. The collection also includes letters to Wesson from Spanish comrades, items relating to his service in the United States Army, and writings by Wesson, both poetry and prose, which reflect his political beliefs and recall the time he spent with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain.
Provenance
The Neil Wesson Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in 1975 by his widow Ruth Wesson. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Neil Wesson, nee Nathan Weisenfeld (1906-1974) was born in Detroit, Michigan to Polish Jewish Orthodox parents. As a young adult, Wesson worked in the mailroom of the Detroit Post Office, as a lumberjack in upper Michigan, and as a chemical worker at Dow in Midland.
Wesson joined the Merchant Marine in 1932 and spent several months fighting the Japanese in Shanghai. Back in Detroit in 1933, seeing the effects of the Depression, Wesson became a dedicated Marxist. He worked as an arc welder in several factories in Detroit and was an active member of the United Auto Workers and the Communist Party before going to Spain in 1937 to fight fascism. Wesson served in Spain as a sergeant in the 15th International Brigade and fought in battles at Jarama, the Ebro River, Brunete, Teruel (the Aragon Offensive) and Madrid. He was wounded several times during his service.
Returning from Spain in 1939, Wesson found that he had been blacklisted and to find employment he changed his name from Nathan (Nate) Weisenfeld to Neil Wesson. Wesson got a job at the Packard Motor Car Company where he was an active union organizer. Wesson was accepted into the United States Army in 1942. He served as a weapons sergeant and reconnaissance scout with the 40th Engineer Combat Regiment. Wesson fought campaigns in France and Italy and during the Battle for Germany, he was among the first to reach and open the gates of the Dachau concentration camp. He was awarded the Legion of Merit for his service in World War II.
After the war, Wesson enrolled at Wayne State University where he earned a degree in Business Administration with a major in Accounting. Finding that he preferred physical labor, Wesson returned to factory work as a welder. Once again, he was an active union member. In the 1950s Wesson began writing free-verse poetry on historical and political topics. In 1970, he published a book of poetry called Man In Ferment. He died in 1974 at the age of 68.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Correspondence. This series contains several letters from Spanish comrades to Neil Wesson during the Spanish Civil War. The bulk of this series and this collection consists of letters from Neil Wesson to his wife, Sarah Wesson, written during the years 1942-1945 while Wesson was serving with the United States Army in World War II.
Series II: General Files. This series contains an unsigned biography of Neil Wesson that describes the nature and sources of his political convictions, his union activities, and his service in the Spanish Civil War and in World War II. The series also contains ephemera relating to Wesson’s service with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, including a cloth insignia and a livret militare from the International Brigades, and a number of items relating to Wesson’s service as a Sergeant the 40th Engineer Combat Regiment of the United States Army, including a recommendation for an award, a citation for a Legion of Merit, and a proposal submitted to the US Army regarding a landing-barge-cradle device that Wesson invented. Finally, the series contains writings by Wesson, including poetry from later in his life that reflects his personality and political beliefs and prose describing some of his experiences with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series. Within the Correspondence series, letters from Neil Wesson to Sarah Wesson are arranged chronologically.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I. Correspondence
II. General Files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Neil Wesson Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Printed ephemera.; Biography files.; Manuscripts (document genre); Correspondence.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Teruel, Battle of, Teruel, Spain, 1937-1938.; Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Madrid (Spain); Jarama River Valley (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Sources.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Wessen, Sarah; Weisenfeld, Nathan
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Liras, Laura to Neil Wesson, undated, Jul 1938, Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Perez, Santiago to Neil Wesson, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified Correspondents to Neil Wesson, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Correspondent to Ruth Wesson, Aug 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade to Sarah Wesson, Jan 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - War Department to Sarah Wesson, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wesson, Neil to Unidentified, 1938, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jan 1942-Mar 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, May 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jun 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jul 1942-Aug 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Sep 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Oct 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Nov 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jan 1943-Mar 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Apr 1943-May 1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jun 1943-Aug 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Sep 1943-Oct 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Wesson Neil to Sarah Wesson, Nov 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Dec 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jan 1944-Feb 1944 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Mar 1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Apr 1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, May 1944-Jun 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jul 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Aug 1944-Sep 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Oct 1944-Nov 1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Dec 1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jan 1945-Feb 1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Mar 1945-Apr 1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, May 1945-Jun 1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Jul 1945-Aug 1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, Sep 1945-Nov 1945 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wesson, Neil to Sarah Wesson, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series II: General Files
  - Biography: Neil Wesson, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Citation for Legion of Merit, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Honorable Discharge from Army of the United States, Nov 1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Insignia: Battalon de la Muerte, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Invention Proposal by Neil Wesson, May 1943-Sep 1943 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Livret Militaire, Brigadas Internacionales, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Memoirs of Time in Spain (typescript), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Memorial Certificate from the United States of America, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Motto: Proposal to 40th Engineer Combat Regiment, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Notes in Spanish and Catalan, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Poetry by Neil Wesson, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Recommendation for Award, Mar 1945 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Salvoconducto (Safe Conduct Pass), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Thanksgiving Day Menu, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - World War II Notes and Ephemera, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 50)